them to say yes hey that's kind of what
we're going to talk about today and
there's no guarantee you know sometimes
you have to go back to the drawing board
several times that happens that's that's
just kind of part of the process being a
grad student who and what not but there
are ways that you can kind of anticipate
what's going to happen and anticipate
and prepare and plan so that hopefully
your committee will say yes i'm in love
with your research topic okay so that's
kind of how we're going to start today
there is a template for the thesis and
there's a template for the dissertation
there is no template for the proposal
there isn't one size fits all for your
thesis or your dissertation proposal
unfortunately or fortunately that is the
case
if you can get your hands on proposals
from other grad students in your program
just to see what they look like what are
the expectations of most of the people
most of the you know people in your
department of your committee member your
chair the other thing is if you don't
have a model to follow you guys all know
the big journals in your field so I
would just go back and look at an
article because basically an article
from your field is going to be the main
skeleton you could work from okay
however that those articles are
constructed so let's take a social
sciences or hard sciences article you
may have an introduction that states the
problem a little background if you're in
social sciences maybe a longer
background a longer literature review a
methodology and he won't have the
results or the discussion right so what
you could do in your proposals you could
have an introduction a little background
lit review and then what you're going to
say though is instead of saying I did or
this research did do this everything's
then flipped in the future tense I will
I proposed the problem i'm going to look
at is this this is why that problem is
important I will I will I will I will I
will and you outline all of that
you can go to the library website and
you can find theses and dissertations in
your program okay have you all have you
all done that that is so cool do you
know you can find them by your advisor
as well if you go to the library website
you go to the database library that
tomato edu databases and put in ProQuest
dissertations and theses full text all
right you get this window okay yeah once
you click on it you get this window okay
you put in a topic you could put in an
author maybe what you put in is maybe
somebody you know who graduated before
you if you wanted to look at their
dissertation or thesis you put in your
advisor and then you put in Texas A&M
and it brings up all the dissertations
or the theses that your advisor chaired
okay what if they don't have any they
may be a new professor or something like
that you can put in a committee member
it's it's nice just to get a ballpark
figure of what the finished product
would look like they want something that
looks like it is academic it is a
proposal that is not half baked it's
realistic we work with a lot of students
who have a great idea for a topic but
it's really important for your committee
to know that you know the research that
has been done before there's a physics
professor that I work with quite a bit
on campus he said he had a grad student
who kept coming to him and saying to him
I have this great idea and the professor
says that my friend the professor says
um not really that was done in like
nineteen eighty six but he but it hasn't
been done my way not really that was
done in 98 right so what kind of
credibility does that student have with
his advisor at that point
it go back and figure out what's been
done so that they know that you're going
to contribute to that body of knowledge
and not just rehash something that
somebody already did right so so it's
kind of like so they're going to ask you
your vices are going to ask you to go
back and do your homework if you come up
with and I did say okay I have a new way
of doing something I know it's going to
work they'll probably say that's great
that's a great idea now go back and show
me how that idea came about okay where
did that idea come from that happens
then in doing that literature review or
that study okay literature reviews I
find trip students up more than anything
else the methodology seems pretty easy
even the results if you're doing a
quantitative study you know ago ok I'm
going to survey this many students or
I'm going to do this you know I'm going
to do this many experiments I'm going to
find out what this happens i'm going to
you know run this statistical test I'm
going to present these results pretty
straightforward right but that
introduction back or how much is enough
you know that usually trip students up a
little bit so figure that out look at
sources that lead to other sources one
of the things that I like to do is when
I'm first exploring a topic I don't
exactly know who the big scholars are in
the field if it's a new topic to me that
makes sense you just don't know so what
I'll do is I'll look at a lot of
literature but you can't put all of that
literature and a literature review that
oh my gosh you have to pick and choose
because there's so many articles out
there have you have you been kind of
overwhelmed when you when you go to even
Google Scholar you go to the Tambu
databases they say you put in a topic
and it says you know 12 million hits you
go I it's overwhelming one of the ways
you can sift that down is saying okay
who are the big players I'm really only
going to refer to the big players in
that field when i do that background
okay who did this who did this who did
this who led to the where I'm going to
take off with my research and what I do
is I go back to google scholar and I put
like i'll be reading sources
reading sources and I'm like I don't
even know if I should include this I
kind of cross reference I go and put it
into google scholar and it says cited by
and there's a number that gives you a
number of all the other journal articles
that have reference that journal article
this article has been cited by seven
hundred other peer reviewed articles hey
you better take a look at it now it may
be cited because it's that bad because
scholars are just talking to each other
right you know this may be the worst
article ever written by this theorist or
whatever and everybody's bashing this
poor person but for good or for bad
you're going to probably bring that up
in your literature review okay what I
work with grad students a lot of times
their scope is I would like to i would
like to have world peace solve world
hunger find clean energy and be better
looking that's what they're going to do
in their dissertation oh my gosh you
know what is attainable you know
sometimes what you want to do is a
life's work and not a thesis or
dissertation so think about scope is
this something that you can do so one of
the things you want to think about is
can I get the data so if you're writing
the proposal think before your professor
asks you what kind of access do I have
under David now y'all in the hard
sciences you probably work in a lab you
probably already know what your topic is
in fact a lot of a lot if you all even
kind of write the proposal after you've
done all the research you don't tell GSF
anyway we're there you know so so the
proposal process is very very not that
big a deal for y'all okay i'm going to
say though i think it's important to do
the literature review up front even if
you don't have to because you have a
much better idea of how your research
your research and your lab fits into the
broader context that's just me even if
your professor doesn't make you do it I
think it's a good idea to do it can I
get the data in the time frame allotted
for my dissertation so maybe you will
graduate we all want to
graduate would you like to graduate
sooner or later okay so think about that
can I get that data in the time frame
that I have for my research am i
addressing one research problem or
multiple to depart that's that world
hunger thing and clean energy okay and
can I articulate my research problem in
a sentence or two this is really
important because in your head
everything makes sense in my head
everything makes sense it's only when I
start talking about it that I realize
that I have some problems with my logic
or my thinking okay because everything
makes perfectly boy I tell you what I
woke up in the morning I have an idea
and I am brilliant you know and then
what's your idea and I start talking
about it I talk in circles and circles
and circles and people start getting
more and more confused okay that's
something to think about as a matter of
fact we're going to do an activity
you
the person next to you writing up the
elevator friendly sort usually we don't
talk on elevators but it happens to be a
friendly sort turns to you and says oh
you're a graduate student what's your
research topic what are you working on
what's your dissertation about and I
want you to tell that person in a sin no
more than two if you're really
struggling three sentences were you guys
talking to each other okay I would like
for you to tell me what her research is
about so when you can say that Savannah
when you say it in a couple of sentences
you go to your chair and you go yep I'm
in a blah blah blah blah blah blah and
I'm going to do it this way blah blah
and they say okay see you later okay
write it up and see you later part of
the process is thinking that through
just because you're looking at you know
minors under the ocean and all of that
and the tools they use and that kind of
stuff that doesn't mean that that came
easily to you just because you can say
it now and I want to make this point for
those of you who are still in your heads
about everything that's a natural part
of the process if you're easy it
wouldn't be grad school it you have
ideas that are new ideas that are
forming and forming and forming that's
part of the process keep digging keep
reading it will happen you will get
there and you will be able to explain
your research very very clearly but make
sure that you just go through the whole
process don't bypass it okay now let's
talk about methodology your committee is
going to want to know why you chose to
look at the problem in the way you chose
to look at the problem that's important
because there are lots of ways to look
at a problem there are lots of ways to
look at a problem there's not one way to
look at a problem okay so is it
important than for you to say when
you're reading these journal articles in
your literature review you're not just
reading them for content I'm you are
reading for content you're looking at
the results and so forth you're also
looking at the methodology they you
to get to that result because it will
inform your decision making a lot in the
process now a lot of a lot of you only
use quantitative methodologies what
information is method capture what
information presented is in this way is
important to my study why is the
information I use an article on hay bale
feeders quite a bit when I work with
animal science students it's very simple
article in terms of like the study that
they use they said okay forage loss it
the problem stated is forage loss is one
of the most important like losses of
farmer can have in terms of inputs
outputs economically so how do they
reduce loss for cattle forage in hay
bale feeders so what I'm talking about
is those round things you always see
they put the big round bales in that and
the cows eat it and that way it doesn't
go to waste okay so what they were
looking at is how much waste does the
design of the feeder make a difference
do aggressive cows get to it does the
design allow for aggressive cows versus
non aggressive cows right and what they
did is there were studies that were done
before but they would tweak them they
tweak the methodology they said what
this person did what this these guys did
is great they really looked at phorage
loss and that was really good but
nobody's looked at the design of the
Bale feeder in terms of the aggressive
non-aggressive cows getting enough Forge
so they also tested the cows to see how
much forage they were getting in that
see what I'm saying so they took a kind
of a like okay this lots of people have
looked at this forest loss but they
tweaked it and made it like with a few
different methods changed it and made it
new okay so what you're looking at in
your methodology is what is everybody
else done to look at the problem and why
isn't the problem solved yet qualitative
methodologies basically is a discovery
process you're kind of going along
discovering it so you're guided by
research questions the set of hypotheses
okay how do people perceive their
experiences
in X ok I know that sounds a little
fuzzy to those of you in engineering
that's ok that's what that's what we do
right how do people perceive what's the
perception and what kind of theory am I
looking at it through social capitalism
or my own social capital or am I looking
at it through feminism and we're looking
at it through you know critical race
theory there are all kinds of ways to
overlay that ok the thing is when you
pick those you just need to know why you
picked them because your committee is
going to ask you that ok so how do you
organize all this information in a way
that your committee will understand
their I'm giving you a couple of
different templates here that you can go
by and it kind of depends on what your
research questions are on how you want
to do this but one way if you have no
guidance from your advisor and you have
no clue this is a shot give it a shot
one do a little introduction to review
of the literature you don't need to
necessarily go crazy if you haven't
gotten a lot of advice from your advisor
I wouldn't do a 40-page literature
review do enough to where you think you
can talk about it give it to your
advisor let him or her kind of guide you
say you know what I like the way you
started on this but you need a whole lot
of information on this this is not your
proposal defense this is just the
initial conversation right okay
statement of the problem purpose of the
study what the heck are you doing this
for because they may ask you that too
why what why why why okay and you don't
want them to tell tell you oh yeah that
was done in 1986 that was done in 1998
you want them to go yeah i buy that I
totally married that proposal okay what
like what in a research question what
questions do you have what questions
you're going to ask to get at that
information and how best what kind of
methodology am I going to use to answer
those questions and then what what would
it mean okay now you can't do the
significance yet because you don't have
the data it's your proposal but in your
head in your head what might this do
okay what could this do
is it important okay all right that's a
thought here's another template just do
em read scientists know this one lab
reports you know em read introduction
you know including a little background
reviewed literature methods you don't
have the results and you don't have the
discussion okay but you have them maybe
a hypothesis or something like that so
you want it you want to understand the
problem why that problem is important to
solve what's been done before to try to
solve the problem why that problem
hasn't been solved yet and what you're
going to do to solve it so what are
these scholars all about you think about
your committee and you think about how
you're going to talk to your committee
on paper with your proposal you want
them to say yes you want to them say yes
i love your proposal i'm in love with
your pole so i will marry your proposal
okay how do you get them to take you
seriously you have to show them that you
can do that work in your proposal
because that's going to lead to that
conversation where they call you that or
if it's in your master's degree it's a
little kind of tighter it's a little
smaller but your masters may lead to
your PhD do you know I'm saying ok so
what they want to see is that you have a
solid knowledge of your topic and then
when they send you out you can talk to
anybody about your about the research
you've done
you
when you go to a party maybe don't know
everybody there you go into a party and
you get there late okay and there are
people talking in the living room you'll
remember what that was like right there
people talking later i'm not talking
about an undergrad party either talking
in the living room talking in the
kitchen talking in their little groups
of people talking right so if you go in
late and you approach a group of people
what do you do first what's the first
thing you introduce yourself hi hi hi hi
hat but if there's a conversation
already going what do you do yeah you do
listening is the literature review you
need to find out what the big dogs in
your field are saying about that topic
so what if you just come in and you're
completely socially awkward I'm not I'm
not looking at anybody in particular
here but you come in and there's a
conversation going on and you just
interrupt the conversation and say well
my ideas blah blah you say something
completely dumb it inappropriate what
happens and they look at you like you're
really awkward okay that's what happens
when you don't do your literature review
and you just decide that that's your
idea and you spout it out for your
committee is that a good analogy so what
you do is you go hit the books and you
read everything there is to read about
that topic and you figure out front
approaches that people have taken to
solve that problem and then once you've
finished listening then you enter the
conversation that's the time so if your
committee says but what about so-and-so
yeah I thought about so-and-so when I
read that but the way that so so
approach this problem doesn't factor in
this whoo now you're having a
conversation with your chair aren't you
that's the back and forth there okay
alright so when you write that
background which seems to trip people up
in the proposal more than anything else
when you write it you're just listening
to what happens you're listening to the
events you're finding out who the big
players are because you know there's
somebody that you know they can say so
than crazy and everybody laughs oh oh
that's great that's great you know
that's a big dog in the field okay you
know that's a big dog everybody's
listening is whoever he's listening to
that's how you lose that google scholar
as well but then you find out what
hasn't been done in your field aha
you're going to fill that gap in the
research you know everybody's looked at
this problem they haven't solved it
because they haven't looked at it this
way if you know that it can articulate
it that proposal almost writes itself
I'm kind of teasing it doesn't but you
know
everybody has an outside member on their
committee is that correct okay I write
my audience is the outside member my
audience in my head when I'm writing I'm
not writing to my chair who is an expert
in my particular topic I write to the
outside member because if the outside
member on your committee can understand
your proposal then everybody in your
committee can understand the proposal
and that means explaining a lot of
things that you want a shortcut
everybody knows that using these
acronyms and these things and blah blah
if you're outside committee member
doesn't understand it explain it so
explain everything theories methyl
methodologies key terms that your
committee members you'll be surprised
they may not be experts on the theory
that you're using so explain it this to
things one it informs committee members
who aren't familiar with your research
about what you're doing but there's even
something more subversive it also tells
your committee that you know what you're
talking about as well
this is I'm going to get in the nuts and
bolts if you guys don't mind how to
write it because they're a lot of people
can have stock in abstraction about how
to do your proposal but I want to talk
about some of the things that trip
people up and help you with that if I
can so really what you're doing in that
background is you're saying what do
other people say okay what do experts in
the field say about X well a number of
studies have suggested that what are
commonplace opinions on X it is accepted
practice too and that maybe assumptive
that is accepted practice to you have to
be careful about that but what is
everybody by what does everybody believe
what does every what is the standard
practice what do people apply or assume
what are both sides of the argument and
those are the things that you can find
in the literature and you want to
indicate back to your committee okay
what are people talking about what Artie
people talking about then you position
yourself in that argument well this is
what someone so it says and I agree with
that but here okay even in life sciences
and so forth you're going to put up the
debate because you're going to find that
gap in the research well so-and-so this
study showed or this study demonstrated
that laying hens at three days have x
salmonella but what wasn't done in that
was taking the sample this way or
whatever see what I'm saying so the next
thing you do after you show what other
people say is you put yourself or you
place yourself in the context of all of
the existing literature out there where
do I fit in okay where does my you know
what came before me where do I fit in
what's lacking and what's out there how
does my research fill the gap and why is
it important because you want to answer
the the big question what's the big
question so what your committee is going
to be nicer than that more polite but
what they want to know is so what so
what's the big deal if you do this
research or not who cares so what you
answer that question
that's getting you closer how do they
say it you can do summary this person
said this this person agreed with this
person but disagreed with this person
this study showed this is study showed
this this study is similar in this way
okay paraphrasing paraphrasing is really
good when you're translating technical
jargon into more laypersons terms it's
really good for that or defining things
paraphrase is not a great writing
strategy it's not so you guys who love
those pdfs and you'll highlight them all
the time and you carry them around with
you and then you start writing your
paper from the pdfs usually that lends
itself to kind of like chunky writing
chunky study you know like oh you know
like it's not in your voice maybe
changed a few words or whatever but it's
paraphrase paraphrases elegant when
you're actually just presenting a fact
in science or translating it not
translating about making some kind of
very complex idea simple okay most
people don't use quotation unless you're
in the humanities some social sciences
do and actually in quotations in the
humanities you're using the quotes as
evidentiary support okay maybe history
too alright so this is for prepare
phrasing you repeat something in new
words you don't just right-click and
pick another word it's ready to a varied
audience when you were really useful
when you present specific results and
then tech information okay direct
quotation it's really a used sparsely in
most of your areas except for english
okay or history or some of this but if
you do use it make sure that you
introduce a quote put the quote in and
then explain the quote what i see a lot
of times when people quote is they
introduce the quote put the quote say
look I'm really too lazy to explain this
quote to you so I'm just going to move
on to my next topic okay you got to come
back and explain that quote and move on
it's your burden you're a burden to
explain the quote to the reader not
anybody else's okay
how you say something matters as much as
what you say right if you want your
advisor to say yes to your proposal how
should you write what do you think
they're looking for easily explained
clear straightforward don't hide don't
be settled one of the things I do go to
my journal how do my journals how do how
do academics write in my journal copy
that style do they use passive voice so
they use active voice do they do this do
they do that
some of you guys will use active voice
in the introduction and background and
passive voice in the methods or vice
versa I can't answer that for you it's
not a one-size-fits-all at all
get organized you're about to amass a
huge number of PDF files get organized
how many of you guys use refworks or
EndNote if you don't get it it's great
if you don't use one or the other
refworks tends to be a little easier to
learn how to use go to the library
website library table edu endnote a lot
of people in the sciences use EndNote
you can get that download that from the
University as well either way okay
whatever works for you is great but
organize yourself Zotero i use the Tarot
sometimes when i'm searching searching
searching and i find something and i'll
download the citation in Zotero it works
in firefox as a firefox plugin it's not
quite as heftiest refworks but it's real
quick and dirty okay so what you don't
want to do is waste time because if you
have to how many of you guys have had to
go back you you read an article then you
had to go find it again and gosh where
was that article you guys don't have
time for that don't you want to graduate
get organized just put everything so in
a location where you're going to find it
attach it you can go ahead then and if
you want to use one of these tools to
write your paper and insert the
citations as you go you can do that I
just used it for my reference pages I
just kept it because I like to do the
citations myself I just kept it and I
said APA 5th edition oh and it turned it
into the APA it's magic i don't know how
it works is fantastic and just stay
organized know what style you're writing
in and then remembered texas A&M
University Writing Center even revelry
comes to us for writing assistance even
revelry so you should be able to also
come see us at the writing center
anytime okay go have fun take care good
luck thank you thank you so much